大家好 这里是Scott Manley
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
几天前 毛子的科学号实验舱把整个国际空间站带跑偏了
A few days ago, the new science module Nauka took the International Space Station for a spin,
大家都想知道跑偏到什么程度
and many of you wanted to know just how much of a spin was involved.
官方说是45度 但我们后来拿到了遥测数据
The official term had been 45 degrees, but we actually had some telemetry from the station.
所以很多人都出来做了各种动画
So ... many of you went and set out to try to render this,
而有意思的事情是 大家都存在一些有趣的问题
and the funny thing is, everybody ran into some interesting problems.
这个图标来自Liam Kennedy 记录了ISS在当时的滚转 俯仰和偏航角
This is a nice graph by Liam Kennedy, which basically takes the roll pitch and yaw of the ISS,
抓取自ISS的实时遥测数据 并绘制出来
which were taken from this ISS live page and graphs them all out.
很多人拿到这张图就想做一个动画出来
And many people decided to take this graph and turn it into actual animation.
这是在NASASpaceFlight论坛上两个人发布的动画
And this is one by erma gerd or Max Steroton on NASA Space Flight that was ...
这也太夸张了
marvelous to see this.
但这并不是真实情况
But ... this is not actually what happened.
虽然动画时间加速了 但国际空间站做的各种机动还是太鬼畜了
It certainly does look like the space station's doing something wild, obviously it's accelerated in time.
实际上动画里很多时刻并没有反映出真实情况
But it has many movements that aren't actually consistent with the real thing,
想了解原因 首先我要让大家知道我自己的想法
and to understand why, first of all, I want to show you my version of what I think happened.
如视频所示 这是我第一次在Blender里做3D 从NASA官网上下了个模型放进去
Yeah, this is my first attempt to do anything in blender, I just grabbed the model from the NASA site.
我把星辰号服务舱放在了下面以表示科学号实验舱的位置
I took, uh, Zvezda and put it on underneath to show where Nauka would be.
上面没加进步号飞船和龙飞船
I haven't added in any Progress or Soyuz or Dragon.
不过大家知道空间站大体外形就好
But you get the idea of the shape of the station, now.
目前它是在向右运动
It is traveling towards the right here,
这种情况并不常见 因为毛子舱段竟然在前
and this is unusual in this orientation, because the Russian section is going first.
通常情况下是国际舱段在前
Normally, the international sanction goes first.
这意味着事件发生之前 国际空间站的姿态相当于是转了180度倒车前进的
And that means that in its orientation, before the event started, it was yawed 180 degrees around.
之后 科学号实验舱点燃了推进器 推动国际空间站
Now what happens is Nauka starts to fire its thrusters to pull away from the station,
导致右侧开始下降 所以空间站姿态会发生视频中所示的变化
and that pulls the right side down, so it begins to pivot around like this,
而进步号飞船和星辰号服务舱上的发动机
and the engines on the Progress and Zvezda
启动并抵抗这股旋转的力量
basically start to counteract this and slow the rotation down.
它们这样抗衡 维持每秒半度的旋转
And they keep a sort of constant rotation rate of about half a degree per second.
最终停下后回到了最初的姿态
Eventually, they stop it and they bring it all the way back around to its original orientation.
整个过程持续约一个多小时 转了大概一圈半
So this took like an hour or so, it completed about one and a half rotations,
这点也得到了在任务控制中心的Zebulon Scoville的确认
and this has been confirmed by mission controller Zebulon Scoville,
事件发生时他刚好在值班
who, uh, was there and act of during this incident.
那为什么其他人的动画里空间站转得那么鬼畜呢？
So why are people getting such wacky rotations in their animations?
我们回来看一下图表
Well, let's take a look at the graph.
重点先看绿线 俯仰角 最初角度大概是0
And the important thing to look at is the green one, the pitch, and that basically starts at roughly zero.
然后增长到90度后开始降低到-90
And then increases until it hits 90 and then starts decreasing until it hits, well, -90.
发生了什么？飞船不是在上下运动 而是在旋转
Guess what? This isn't going up and down, right? This is rotating around,
因为俯仰角的定义域就是-90到90度
because the pitch is being capped between 90 ... +90 and -90.
然后我们再看红线和蓝线 对应滚转和偏航
Now, if you look at the red and the blue line for the roll and the pitch,
当绿线达到90度的临界值时
when the green line hits one of its 90 degree limits,
俯仰和偏航会瞬间大幅变化 原因是……
they flip around, they take these big transitions, and that's because ...
空间站旋转到了角度值的奇点 懂吗？
The space station orientation is moving what through what we call a singularity, right?
在正负90度的时候 俯仰和偏航会变成相同的东西
At +90 and -90, both the roll and the yaw become the same thing.
所以此时它们会瞬间交换位置 会有一个突变
So when it comes out of that, they can swap places, they can transition.
最好的理解方法是想象你头顶正飞过一架飞机
The the best way to think about it is if you imagine watching a plane coming towards you,
当它向你飞来的时候 你的头会越抬越高
and as it comes towards you, you lift your head higher and higher.
当飞过你正上方的时候 你会突然一个很快速的转身
And then as it passes over the top, you need to turn around very quickly,
不然你会向后仰过去摔倒
or you end up falling over on your back.
这种情况的另一个形式就是万向锁
Now, the other term for this situation is gimble Lock.
就是当你进行三轴旋转的时候
That's basically where you have three axes of rotation,
转到某一个位置 会让其中两轴完全重合
and when you move to certain positions, you can end up with two of your axes aligned,
从而失去一个自由度
and you lose one of your axes.
这也是阿波罗飞船上要非常注意的一个事情 因为他们用的就是三轴导航
And of course this was a big thing in flying the Apollo spacecraft, because they had three axis navigation.
如果飞船指向了某个特定区域
And if the spacecraft ever pointed into one of these regions,
万向节就需要旋转无限快才能正确定向
the gimbles would have to move infinitely fast to correctly track.
这可能导致他们在太空中迷向 因此飞船上专门有个警报灯
And they could lose orientation, so they had a warning light
告知他们在接近万向节锁死的区域 不要靠近
to tell them when they were getting close to these so that they didn't get into that situation.
而偏航 俯仰和滚转都是对人来说很直观 很好理解的东西
So and with yaw pitch and roll are shown are really, for humans, there's something that we understand,
而他们数学上也叫作欧拉角
but they also represent mathematically Euler angles.
也因此 欧拉角的缺点就是存在奇点
And yeah, Euler angles have their problems with their singularities.
因此在计算机里 这些旋转通常是用四元数描述的
Internally, they're represented by something called quaternions,
如果你搞过3D游戏
and if you've ever made 3D video games,
你可能遇到过四元数 因为它用来表示旋转非常方便
you've probably encountered these because there are really useful ways of representing orientation.
性质非常好 便于操作 而且没有奇点的问题
They have all these nice properties, how you can operate on them and they don't have all these singularities.
大家也可以看看视频中
And if you look at the video, I showed
ISS的实际遥测数据 就能直接看到它用的四元数
with the actual telemetry on screen, you can see the quaternions listed in there.
它们的标签叫"LVLH QTRN"  结尾是0-3 一共四个数
They show up as "LVLH QTRN", and you've got zero through three,
因为是四维空间的数据
because it's a four dimensional number.
就好像增加第四个万向节防止万向锁一样
It's just like adding a fourth gimble ring to avoid gimble lock,
你添加一个额外的维度 就神奇地得到了这样一个性质非常好的四元数
you add an extra dimension, and magically, you know, have this very useful set of properties.
而且这背后还有一段有趣的历史
And you know, this is an interesting bit of history.
四元数是由一位叫哈密顿的物理学家 数学家发明的
The quaternions were invented by a guy called Hamilton who was a physicist and a mathematician,
就是在经典力学里“哈密顿量”的那个哈密顿 不是撞出51G的那个
if you've ever encountered Hamiltonian in your classical mechanics, that's him.
当时人们已经知道复数可以表示平面上的旋转操作
And ... at the time, it was known that complex numbers could be used to represent rotations in a plane.
大家应该也知道 复数是一个实部一个虚部 虚数单位i=√(-1)
And you know how you have the real part and the complex part with the value i the square root of -1.
而哈密顿想利用复数构造一个三维的旋转
So Hamilton wanted to generalize this to three dimensional rotations.
于是他一开始是一个实部+两个虚部
So he tried to do a version with a real part and an imaginary part and a secondary imaginary part,
结果数学上卡壳了 整个系统无法自洽
and he could never make the math work, he could never be self consistent,
而之后他想明白了 他需要的不是两个虚部 而是三个
and he had this sort of moment of revelation that he needed three imaginary parts and one real part.
这里最传奇的故事就是这灵光一闪的时刻发生时 他在都柏林布鲁姆桥上
And the legend is, he had this flash of inspiration while crossing the Broome Bridge in Dublin.
所以那座桥上也立了一块石碑 来纪念他发现了重要的四元数
So ... that bridge actually has the equations carved into it to commemorate, it's that important.
当然 在当时那个时候 这只是一个小的数学结构
Of course, at the time, they were just a mathematical construct,
到了今天大家才发现性质非常好 有很多用处
which had nice properties these days is essential to all sorts of applications.
很多物理问题需要用到四元数来解决
There are physics problems that require them to be solved.
现在很多游戏制作 3D图形领域
They're obviously used to make video games, 3D graphics.
四元数通常会用来表示诸如机器人 或是航天器的旋转
They're used for representing, like rotations in robots and spacecraft.
这就是四元数背后的一段有趣的历史
So yeah, interesting sideline in history, there.
结尾这里我想再给大家放一段Liam Kennedy发的视频
And so I just want to end with a little bit of footage, again, compiled by Liam Kennedy.
这是空间站在翻滚时拍摄地球的画面
This is a nadir looking camera as we pan upwards,
大家能清楚看到亚洲上空城市的灯光
and the great thing here is you see the city lights as they pass over Asia.
这种动态的场面可不是空间站上随便能看到的
Not every day you get those kind of dynamic views from the space station.
还是挺有意思的！
And that's a good thing!
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
I'm Scott Manley, fly safe.